<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

<channel>
	<title>tree mortality &#8211; The Biogoegraphy &amp; Landscape Dynamics Lab</title>
	<atom:link href="https://tjassal.github.io/LabWebsite/tag/tree-mortality/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://tjassal.github.io/LabWebsite/</link>
	<description>Research focused on biogeography, spatial ecology and landscape change at Kent State University</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2014 23:27:48 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.2</generator>
<site xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">77891341</site>	<item>
		<title>New paper offers retrospective view of the 1970s mountain pine beetle outbreak in Glacier National Park</title>
		<link>https://tjassal.github.io/LabWebsite/2014/12/09/new-paper-offers-retrospective-view-of-the-1970s-mountain-pine-beetle-outbreak-in-glacier-national-park/</link>
				<comments>https://tjassal.github.io/LabWebsite/2014/12/09/new-paper-offers-retrospective-view-of-the-1970s-mountain-pine-beetle-outbreak-in-glacier-national-park/#respond</comments>
				<pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2014 19:44:43 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[tim.assal@gmail.com]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog-lite]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bark Beetle Outbreak]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[color-infrared]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dendroctonus ponderosae]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[electromagnetic spectrum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Forest Disturbance]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Glacier National Park]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Landsat MSS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mountain Pine Beetle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NDVI time series]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Red Attack Phase]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[remote sensing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spatial Statistics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spectral trajectory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tree mortality]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://tjassal.github.io/LabWebsite/?p=706</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[We recently published a new paper in the journal Remote Sensing of Environment, entitled “Modeling a Historical Mountain Pine Beetle Outbreak Using Multiple Lines of Evidence.” We have developed a new method for reconstructing past (1970s) bark beetle outbreaks using a novel combination of aerial photography and Landsat imagery. The lack of spatially explicit data &#8230; <a href="https://tjassal.github.io/LabWebsite/2014/12/09/new-paper-offers-retrospective-view-of-the-1970s-mountain-pine-beetle-outbreak-in-glacier-national-park/" class="more-link">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">New paper offers retrospective view of the 1970s mountain pine beetle outbreak in Glacier National Park</span> <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We recently published a new paper in the journal <a title="RSE December 2014" href="http://www.journals.elsevier.com/remote-sensing-of-environment" target="_blank"><em>Remote Sensing of Environment</em></a>, entitled “Modeling a Historical Mountain Pine Beetle Outbreak Using Multiple Lines of Evidence.” We have developed a new method for reconstructing past (1970s) bark beetle outbreaks using a novel combination of aerial photography and Landsat imagery. The lack of spatially explicit data on this disturbance represents both a major data gap and a critical research challenge in that wildfire fire has removed some of the evidence from the landscape. We utilized multiple lines of evidence to model forest canopy mortality as a proxy for beetle outbreak severity.</p>
<p>The driving concept of the analysis was to map tree mortality in aerial photos and “scale-up” the information to a time series of satellite images. Color-infrared photography utilizes areas of the electromagnetic spectrum that are not visible to the human eye. Living vegetation absorbs blue and red light energy, while radiation in the green and near-infrared portion of the spectrum is reflected. Therefore, the reflectance captured in color-infrared photos can be used to distinguish between areas of live trees and dead trees (see the figure below). Satellite images do not contain the detail of aerial photos, but they allow us to track the reflectance of an area, known as the spectral trajectory, over time. The changes in a spectral trajectory provide clues as to the condition of forest with regard to mountain pine beetle activity.</p>
<p>This project is a critical first step in our overall goal to identify the ecological consequences of the interactions of bark beetles with subsequent fire events over the last several decades in the US Rocky Mountains. The work presents a quantitative application of remote sensing to forest disturbance and is timely given the recent mountain pine beetle outbreak throughout western North America. Furthermore, we believe the paper establishes a platform for future research of historical forest disturbance that would be very beneficial to the field of forest ecology.</p>
<figure id="attachment_790" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-790" style="width: 474px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="https://i1.wp.com/www.timassal.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/RSE_fig2.jpg"><img class="size-large wp-image-790" src="https://i1.wp.com/www.timassal.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/RSE_fig2.jpg?resize=474%2C374" alt="(Left) Landscape photo taken in the Summer of 1980 showing a mixture of live and dead trees in the red attack stage in Waterton Valley (source: Glacier National Park Research Library). (Right) A color-infrared aerial photo of the same area acquired in October 1980 (source: NASA/Glacier National Park). Themosaic of live and dead forest can be identified in both images. The letters correspond to the same area in each photo (A= stream confluence, B= small patch of live trees, surrounded by dead forest, C= linear ribbon of dead forest)." width="474" height="374" srcset="https://i1.wp.com/www.timassal.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/RSE_fig2.jpg?resize=1024%2C808&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i1.wp.com/www.timassal.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/RSE_fig2.jpg?resize=300%2C236&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i1.wp.com/www.timassal.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/RSE_fig2.jpg?w=948 948w, https://i1.wp.com/www.timassal.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/RSE_fig2.jpg?w=1422 1422w" sizes="(max-width: 474px) 100vw, 474px" data-recalc-dims="1" /></a><figcaption id="caption-attachment-790" class="wp-caption-text">(Left) Landscape photo taken in the Summer of 1980 showing a mixture of live and dead trees in the red attack stage in Waterton Valley (source: Glacier National Park Research Library). (Right) A color-infrared aerial photo of the same area acquired in October 1980 (source: NASA/Glacier National Park). The mosaic of live and dead forest can be identified in both images. The letters correspond to the same area in each photo (A= stream confluence, B= small patch of live trees, surrounded by dead forest, C= linear ribbon of dead forest).</figcaption></figure>
<p><em><strong>*Header Photo</strong> – View of Upper Waterton Lake, looking north into Canada. Patches of live and dead trees can be seen on the adjoining slopes. The dead trees are indicative of the “red attack” stage (orange/red needles) and were likely killed by beetles within 1 to 3 years before the photo was taken in the summer of 1980. (Photo provided by the Glacier National Park Research Library).</em></p>
<p><strong><em>Manuscript Abstract</em></strong></p>
<p>Mountain pine beetles are significant forest disturbance agents, capable of inducing widespread mortality in coniferous forests in western North America. Various remote sensing approaches have assessed the impacts of beetle outbreaks over the last two decades. However, few studies have addressed the impacts of historical mountain pine beetle outbreaks, including the 1970s event that impacted Glacier National Park. The lack of spatially explicit data on this disturbance represents both a major data gap and a critical research challenge in that wildfire has removed some of the evidence from the landscape. We utilized multiple lines of evidence to model forest canopy mortality as a proxy for outbreak severity. We incorporate historical aerial and landscape photos, aerial detection survey data, a nine-year collection of satellite imagery and abiotic data. This study presents a remote sensing based framework to (1) relate measurements of canopy mortality from fine-scale aerial photography to coarse-scale multispectral imagery and (2) classify the severity of mountain pine beetle affected areas using a temporal sequence of Landsat data and other landscape variables. We sampled canopy mortality in 261 plots from aerial photos and found that insect effects on mortality were evident in changes to the Normalized Difference Vegetation Index (NDVI) over time. We tested multiple spectral indices and found that a combination of NDVI and the green band resulted in the strongest model. We report a two-step process where we utilize a generalized least squares model to account for the large-scale variability in the data and a binary regression tree to describe the small-scale variability. The final model had a root mean square error estimate of 9.8% canopy mortality, a mean absolute error of 7.6% and an R<sup>2 </sup>of 0.82. The results demonstrate that a model of percent canopy mortality as a continuous variable can be developed to identify a gradient of mountain pine beetle severity on the landscape.</p>
<p>Assal, T.J., Sibold, J., and R. Reich. 2014. <a title="RSE Article" href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0034425714003435" target="_blank">Modeling a Historical Mountain Pine Beetle Outbreak Using Landsat MSS and Multiple Lines of Evidence.</a> <em>Remote Sensing of Environment </em>155:275-288.<em> </em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://tjassal.github.io/LabWebsite/2014/12/09/new-paper-offers-retrospective-view-of-the-1970s-mountain-pine-beetle-outbreak-in-glacier-national-park/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
						<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">706</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research Presentation at ForestSAT 2014</title>
		<link>https://tjassal.github.io/LabWebsite/2014/11/05/research-presentation-at-forestsat-2014/</link>
				<comments>https://tjassal.github.io/LabWebsite/2014/11/05/research-presentation-at-forestsat-2014/#comments</comments>
				<pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2014 09:10:32 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[tim.assal@gmail.com]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog-lite]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Colorado]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[drought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ForestSAT 2014]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Landsat]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[remote sensing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[time series]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tree mortality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wyoming]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://tjassal.github.io/LabWebsite/?p=712</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[I will present my research on the impacts of drought to aspen and conifer communities at the ForestSAT 2014 Conference in Riva del Garda, Italy (http://forestsat2014.com/). My presentation will take place in the Forest Health track on Wednesday November 5. Spatial and temporal analysis of drought impacts on semi-arid woodlands Palazzo dei Congressi Room: Sala &#8230; <a href="https://tjassal.github.io/LabWebsite/2014/11/05/research-presentation-at-forestsat-2014/" class="more-link">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Research Presentation at ForestSAT 2014</span> <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
								<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I will present my research on the impacts of drought to aspen and conifer communities at the ForestSAT 2014 Conference in Riva del Garda, Italy (<a href="http://forestsat2014.com/">http://forestsat2014.com/</a>). My presentation will take place in the Forest Health track on Wednesday November 5.</p>
<p><em><strong>Spatial and temporal analysis of drought impacts on semi-arid woodlands</strong></em></p>
<p>Palazzo dei Congressi<br />
Room: Sala 300; 16.15-17.45</p>
<p><strong>Abstract</strong></p>
<p>Semi-arid woodlands located on prominent ridges in the Wyoming Basin ecoregion (USA) form an important link between the northern and southern Rocky Mountains. The Little Mountain Ecosystem provides important habitat for many wildlife species and grazing of domestic livestock is an important land use. Woodland communities are dominated by quaking aspen and several conifer species that persist at the xeric fringes of their range in a vast matrix of sagebrush steppe. The area is subject to periodic drought, yet little is known about the impacts of drought on these communities.</p>
<p>Multiple studies have documented a recent increase in mortality rates of coniferous species in western North America (Allen et al., 2010; Breshears et al., 2005; van Mantgem et al., 2009) due to increased water deficit associated with drought and secondary agents such as bark beetle outbreaks. Extensive drought related mortality of quaking aspen has been documented in the boreal forest-parkland ecotone in Canada (Michaelian et al., 2011) and in parts of Colorado, USA (Worrall et al., 2008). Ecotones are important barometers of climate change and we suspect tree stress, dieback or mortality from recent severe droughts.</p>
<p>The use of temporal remotely sensed data has been effective in monitoring drought induced changes in forests and woodlands (Maselli, 2004; Vogelmann et al., 2012). A primary challenge in spectral change analysis is to segregate long term vegetation change from interannual phenology differences in response to fluctuation in climate. We sought to quantify the spatial and temporal impacts of recent drought in an ecosystem that is expected to be vulnerable to drought stress and climate change impacts. A long-term objective of our research is to develop a program to identify and monitor gradual woodland change from abrupt disturbance (e.g. wildfire or management treatments) over large areas of southwest Wyoming.</p>
<p>We used a 13 year collection of MODIS vegetation indices (MOD13Q1) to characterize annual woodland phenology to identify the window of peak greenness. We utilized SPOT-5 imagery to exploit phenological differences to map woodland cover type using classification and regression tree analysis. Our results confirm that woodlands occupy a much smaller percentage of the landscape as compared to regional land cover data. Furthermore, our results describe the spatial heterogeneity of woodland patches (greater number of patches, smaller mean patch size) that is not captured by regional data. This information is critical for accurate measurement of edge density as extensive herbivory of aspen is an important management concern in woodland regeneration.</p>
<p>We also assembled a long-term (&gt;25 years) data set of Landsat TM imagery to estimate the impacts of drought on photosynthetic activity (PA) of the woodlands. We tested multiple vegetation indices to identify anomalies in the long-term trend. PA in the years following drought typically resulted in one of three trajectories. Persistent woodlands rebounded after drought periods, whereas PA of woodlands experiencing mortality exhibited a sharp decrease. A third trajectory exhibited decreasing PA over numerous years following a drought period. These areas exhibited lag effects of the drought, including conifer mortality from biotic agents. Recent field data was collected to measure plot level mortality, but this does not provide information on the timing of mortality. Our results do not indicate widespread tree mortality, but instead delineate portions of the landscape that are highly vulnerable to drought (rapid mortality), experience lag effects (delayed mortality), or resiliency (persistence). Challenges associated with remote sensing of semi-arid woodlands relate to the open canopy of aspen communities and understory vegetation that may obscure the spectral impact of change. The results demonstrate the utility of time-series analysis from readily available remote sensing data. Furthermore, the approach holds potential to monitor localized, gradual change over broad spatial and temporal scales to aid management of this unique ecosystem.</p>
<p><strong>References</strong></p>
<p>Allen, C. D., Macalady, A. K., Chenchouni, H., Bachelet, D., McDowell, N., Vennetier, M., Kitzberger, T., Rigling, A., Breshears, D. D., Hogg, E. H. (Ted), Gonzalez, P., Fensham, R., Zhang, Z., Castro, J., Demidova, N., Lim, J.-H., Allard, G., Running, S. W., Semerci, A., &amp; Cobb, N. (2010). A global overview of drought and heat-induced tree mortality reveals emerging climate change risks for forests. Forest Ecology and Management, 259(4), 660–684. doi:10.1016/j.foreco.2009.09.001</p>
<p>Breshears, D. D., Cobb, N. S., Rich, P. M., Price, K. P., Allen, C. D., Balice, R. G., Romme, W. H., Kastens, J. H., Floyd, M. L., Belnap, J., Anderson, J. J., Myers, O. B., &amp; Meyer, C. W. (2005). Regional vegetation die-off in response to global-change-type drought. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America, 102(42), 15144–8. doi:10.1073/pnas.0505734102</p>
<p>Maselli, F. (2004). Monitoring forest conditions in a protected Mediterranean coastal area by the analysis of multiyear NDVI data. Remote Sensing of Environment, 89(4), 423–433. doi:10.1016/j.rse.2003.10.020</p>
<p>Michaelian, M., Hogg, E. H., Hall, R. J., &amp; Arsenault, E. (2011). Massive mortality of aspen following severe drought along the southern edge of the Canadian boreal forest. Global Change Biology, 17(6), 2084–2094. doi:10.1111/j.1365-2486.2010.02357.x</p>
<p>Van Mantgem, P. J., Stephenson, N. L., Byrne, J. C., Daniels, L. D., Franklin, J. F., Fulé, P. Z., Harmon, M. E., Larson, A. J., Smith, J. M., Taylor, A. H., &amp; Veblen, T. T. (2009). Widespread increase of tree mortality rates in the western United States. Science, 323, 521–524. doi:10.1126/science.1165000</p>
<p>Vogelmann, J. E., Xian, G., Homer, C., &amp; Tolk, B. (2012). Monitoring gradual ecosystem change using Landsat time series analyses: Case studies in selected forest and rangeland ecosystems. Remote Sensing of Environment, 122, 92–105. doi:10.1016/j.rse.2011.06.027</p>
<p>Worrall, J. J., Egeland, L., Eager, T., Mask, R. a., Johnson, E. W., Kemp, P. a., &amp; Shepperd, W. D. (2008). Rapid mortality of Populus tremuloides in southwestern Colorado, USA. Forest Ecology and Management, 255(3-4), 686–696. doi:10.1016/j.foreco.2007.09.071</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
							<wfw:commentRss>https://tjassal.github.io/LabWebsite/2014/11/05/research-presentation-at-forestsat-2014/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
						<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">712</post-id>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
